Zihang Song

PhD Student in Information and Communication Systems, 6GIC, University of Surrey

Personal Homepage: https://szh1456.github.io/

Email: zihang.song@surrey.ac.uk

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is at the intersection of learning-driven **cognitive-communication and signal processing**. I am especially interested in solving the sparse inverse problems from compressive samples of the wideband radio signals and practical sensing matrices designed by optimization and learning methods.

I am passionate about **hardware design of state-of-the-art communication systems**. I have developed the first known prototype of the uniform periodic sampling architecture (<u>link</u>), which achieves sparse spectrum sensing over 2G Hz bandwidth by sampling at an average rate of 400M Hz. I am also interested in the development of software-defined transceiver platforms.

EDUCATION

2020 – Now	University of Surrey	PhD Candidate.	Information and (Communication S	vstems, 6GIC

- Postgraduate Researcher, EPSRC project GHz bandwidth sensing (GBSense)
- Thesis (about to submit): Compressed Spectrum Sensing Based on a Periodic Nonuniform Sub-Nyquist Sampling Framework: from Theory to Practice
- Supervisors: Prof Yue Gao and Prof Rahim Tafazolli

2019-2020	Queen Mary University of London, PhD Student, Electronic engineering
2016-2018	Beihang University, China, MSc, Radio Physics (Frist Class)
2012-2016	Beihang University, China, BSc, Applied Physics (First Class)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCES

Research Assistant, EPSRC Fellowship Project GHz Bandwidth Sensing (GBSense),

2019 - Now

- Compressed spectrum sensing (CSS) framework design and hardware verification for mmWave communication
- Signal processing software and interface development on portable Linux platform (C Language and C++ based on Qt Environment, with python script embedded)
- FPGA development of interleaved high-speed data transmission (VHDL and Verilog on Lattice/Xilinx FPGA)
- Embedded system development for the CSS system (C Language on low-power MCU)
- Software development on National Instruments mmWave Transceiver System (LabVIEW)
- Design and manage the website www.gbsense.net for data sharing and research cooperation
- DNN-based Sub-Nyquist automatic modulation recognition

Research Assistant, NSFC Deep Space Environment Frequency Modulation Atomic Force Microscopy,

2016 - 2019

- Amplitude control algorithm based on Kalman filter for frequency-modulated AFM and FPGA development
- · Fast image reconstruction algorithm based on Bayesian compressed sensing

Principle Investigator, National Undergraduate Innovation & Entrepreneurship Program

2015 - 2016

REVIEWERSHIPS

- IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing
- IEEE Transactions on Cognitive Communications and Networking
- IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology
- IEEE Internet of Things Journal
- Frontiers of Computer Science

TEACHING ACTIVITES

 Teaching assistant, EEE1028 – Laboratories, Design & Professional Studies, 	2020
Undergraduate thesis tutor	2018
 Teaching assistant, Undergraduate Physical Experiments 	2016 - 2018
FUNDINGS AND AWARDS	
Huawei Funding Studentship	2020 - 2022

•	Huawei Funding Studentship	2020 - 2022
•	QMUL Electronic Engineering and Computer Science Research Studentship	2019 - 2020
•	QMUL Doctoral College Initiative Fund	2019
•	Outstanding Graduate Student	2018
•	Departmental Graduate Study Scholarship	2016 - 2018
•	Outstanding Award of National Undergraduate Innovation and Entrepreneurship Program (as PI)	2015 - 2016

2015

PUBLICATIONS

• Guanghua Outstanding Undergraduate Scholarship

Journal Papers

- [J1] **Z. Song**, J. Yang, H. Zhang, and Y. Gao, "Approaching Sub-Nyquist Boundary: Optimized Compressed Spectrum Sensing Based on Multicoset Sampler for Multiband Signal," IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing, vol. 70, pp. 4225-4238, 2022.
- [J2] **Z. Song**, Y. Gao, and R. Tafazolli, "A Survey on Spectrum Sensing and Learning Technologies for 6G," *IEICE Transactions on Communications*, vol. 104, no. 10, pp. 1207–1216, 2021.
- [J3] Y. Gao, **Z. Song**, H. Zhang, S. Fuller, A. Lambert, Z. Ying, P. Mähönen, Y. Eldar, S. Cui, M.D. Plumbley, C. Parini and A. Nallanathan, "Sub-Nyquist Spectrum Sensing and Learning Challenge," *Frontiers of Computer Science*, vol. 15, no. 4, pp. 1–5, 2021.
- [J4] J. Yang, **Z. Song**, Y. Gao, X. Gu and Z. Feng, "Adaptive Compressed Spectrum Sensing for Multiband Signals," *IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications*, vol. 20, no. 11, pp. 7642–7654, 2021.
- [J5] Y. Zhang, Y. Li, Z. Song, Z. Wang, J. Qian, and J. Yao, "A Novel Method to Remove Impulse Noise from Atomic Force Microscopy Images based on Bayesian Compressed Sensing," *Beilstein Journal of Nanotechnology*, vol. 10, no. 1, pp. 2346–2356, 2019.
- [J6] R. Lin, Y. Li, Y. Zhang, T. Wang, Z. Wang, Z. Song, Z. Dou, and J. Qian, "Design of a Flexure-Based Mixed-Kinematic XY High-Precision Positioning Platform with Large Range," *Mechanism and Machine Theory*, vol. 142, p. 103609, 2019.
- [J7] Y. Li, L. Zhang, G. Shan, **Z. Song**, R. Yang, H. Li, and J. Qian, "A Homemade Atomic Force Microscope Based on a Quartz Tuning Fork for Undergraduate Instruction," *American Journal of Physics*, vol. 84, no. 6, pp. 478–482, 2016.
- [J8] H. Liu, Y. Li, Y. Zhang, Y. Chen, **Z. Song** Z. Wang, S. Zhang, and J. Qian, "Intelligent Tuning Method of PID Parameters Based on Iterative Learning Control for Atomic Force Microscopy," *Micron*, vol. 104, pp.26–36, 2018.
- [J9] Y. Zhang, Y. Li, Z. Wang, Z. Song, R. Lin, J. Qian, and J. Yao, "A Fast Image Reconstruction Method Based on Bayesian Compressed Sensing for the Undersampled AFM Data with Noise," *Measurement Science and Technology*, vol. 30, no. 2, p. 025402, 2019.
- [J10] Z. Wang, J. Qian, Y. Li, Y. Zhang, G. Shan, Z. Dou, Z. Song and R Lin, "Time-frequency Analysis of the Tip Motion in Liquids Using the Wavelet Transform in Dynamic Atomic Force Microscopy," 2018. Nanotechnology, vol. 29, no. 38, p. 385702, 2018.
- [J11] Y. Li, **Z. Song**, Y. Zhang, Z. Wang, Z. Xu, R. Lin, and J. Qian, "A Double-Electrolyte Etching Method of High-Quality Tungsten Probe for Undergraduate Scanning Tunneling Microscopy and Atomic Force Microscopy Experiments," *European Journal of Physics*, vol. 40, no. 2, p. 025004, 2019.

Conference Papers

- [C1] Z. Song, H. Qi, and Y. Gao, "Real-time Multi-Gigahertz Sub-Nyquist Spectrum Sensing System for mmWave," in *Proc.*ACM Millimeter-wave Networks and Sensing Systems, Los Cabos, Mexico, Oct. 2019, pp. 33–38
- [C2] J. Yang, **Z. Song**, Y. Gao, and X. Gu, "Cross Validation Based Adaptive Compressed Spectrum Sensing without Testing Set," in *in IEEE GLOBECOM*, Taipei, Taiwan, Dec. 2020, pp. 1–6.
- [C3] Z. Song, Y. Li, Y. Zhang, R. Lin, Z. Wang, and J. Qian, "A Novel Amplitude Control Algorithm for Frequency-Modulation Atomic Force Microscope Based on Kalman Filter", in *International Congress on Microscopy & Spectroscopy*, Istanbul, Turkey, May 2019, pp. 148.

UNPUBLISED WORKS

- [U1] **Z. Song**, Y She, H. Zhang, and Y. Gao, "Hardware-based Sensing Matrix Optimization for Sub-Nyquist Spectrum Sensing", *IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications* (Under review)
- [U2] Z. Song, H Zhang, S Fuller, A Lambert, Z Ying, P Mähönen, Y Eldar, S Cui, M.D Plumbley, C Parini, A Nallanathan, and Y Gao. "Numerical Evaluation on Sub-Nyquist Spectrum Reconstruction Methods," Frontiers of Computer Science (Under review).
- [U3] H. Zhang, **Z. Song**, and Y. Gao, "Adversarial Autoencoder Empowered Joint Anomaly Detection and Signal Reconstruction from Sub-Nyquist Samples," *IEEE Transactions on Cognitive Communications and Networking* (Under review).
- [U4] **Z. Song**, and Y. Gao, "Software Defined Compressed Spectrum Sensing at Millimeter-Wave for Ubiquitous IoT", *IEEE Internet of Things Journal* (Under review).

SKILLS

Programming languages

• MATLAB, Python, C, C++, Verilog/VHDL, SQL, and LabVIEW

Platforms

- Simulation: MATLAB/SIMUINK, Python
- SDR platforms: LabVIEW, GNURadio
- Circuit design: Altium Designer, Cadence (Orcad)
- FPGA development: ISE/Vivado (for Xilinx), Diamond (for Lattice), LabVIEW (For NI)
- MCU: Keil μVision
- Application and UI development: Visual Studio, Qt